all right hello everyone it is week
11.
and we're in chapter five part two
of the active textbook group first
cohort
will be now turning to some of the more
direct questions on chapter five after
having more of a overview
last week
we'll also
um
be concluding our regular chapter
discussions
for the first part of this book
and in the coming two weeks we'll be
having some review and synthesis
and connecting some dots
asking overarching questions returning
to questions that were based in a
specific chapter and hopefully people
like on their own or wherever else
they're seeing is relevant
or requesting new pages if they see
something that they want
providing some synthesis on this first
half of the textbook which is the
epistemic half and then
um for people who want to continue
in the textbook group
go to the onboarding page
and there's two columns there's yes for
part two of cohort one chapter six
through ten so check that box if you
want to be included in starting in
September
going through chapters 6 through 10
which has like the recipe for active
models and that's when we're going to be
getting more Hands-On with the modeling
also everyone is welcome to join for
part one chapters one through five
cohort two also starting in September
so it could be
um a fun experience just to get another
coat of paint on the material
play more active role ask another set of
questions informed by what you've seen
in the first cohort so feel free to um
check those boxes
and then also
[Music]
um
keep incubating as we head into chapter
um six and Beyond in the second half of
the textbook
um like the project ideas several
um of the project ideas like related to
what Mike and Noah have added we've
started to address and explore in the
active block runs meetings on Wednesday
especially related to like cyber
physical systems simulations
taxonomies for governance
these kinds of ideas
um Brock's added some great notes about
like what what is the ramp that gets
someone to the low road or the high road
um and then uh I've recorded the first
chapter
and the first segments as an audiobook
the first chapter doesn't have any
equations so it's
straightforward to read but the
subsequent chapters do have equations
which is um
motivating
having the natural language
representations of the equations
so there's still a ton of
um discourse questions that can be asked
why things are one way why things are a
different way if it can be placed into
the equation itself that's great if it
needs to be somewhere else hopefully the
space exists and people can request if
not but
um for example when reading the textbook
the equations can be read this way so
those are just some of the projects
that people can look forward to and the
affordances to continue on which is
again uh going to the onboarding and
participating in first five chapters
again cohort two or going to continue on
with chapters six through ten starting
in September for both of these so that
we can like complete one pass of the
book by the end of the year and also
probably make a lot of progress on
different project ideas and project
ideas arising as we start to see and
build templates for the models
and also like Ali has some nice
interactive notebooks so there will be a
lot of great things um coming together
if anyone wants to raise their hand of
course just go for it
otherwise we will be continuing with
the
questions asked about chapter five
before we go to the questions is there
any general comment that somebody wants
to add about
chapter five the reading of it they're
rereading of it listening to the video
from last week
how is chapter five
um
hitting them today
okay
um to kind of maybe bring that one step
closer to a specific question
I'm not going to
read this whole quote but this question
says in the preface
they wrote in chapter 5 we will move
from formal treatments to biological
implications of active inference
this AIDS in mapping the abstract
computational principles of active
inference to specific neural
computations that can be executed by
physiological substrates
this is important in forming hypotheses
under this framework and ensures that
these are answerable to measure data in
other words chapter 5 sets out the
process Theory associated with active
inference
is this how people
saw chapter 5
do they feel like it did something
different did it succeed
at making the abstract computational
principles linked or mapped to specific
neural computations executed by
physiological substrates
yes Eric
you know first of all I have to
apologize I only watched half of last
year's last week's discussion
so I may be cut talking about ground
that's been covered before
um it just seems to me that you know
I've seen many many
I
um papers
um trying to map theories onto brain
circuitry and physiology
and it's
I I'm not well enough
um you know I spent you know I'm only
loosely associated with neuroscience and
you know
don't follow it very closely so it's
hard for me to cite specific instances
along the way I know you mentioned
numanta which is um you know one of the
more recent ones it's
trying to say this is these are what the
layers are doing
um so
this chapter to me didn't seem
um any very qualitatively different from
anybody else's very hand-wavy way to say
here's what the computations are all
about and here here's how they map to uh
what brain circuitry could map to what
base circuitry might be doing it's all
quite hand wavy I I find and
um
I guess plausible but um
it's certainly not definitive nothing
close to that so
um
maybe one other
one other comment I would say is um
again in this chapter they use this word
prediction
in a way that conforms to the theory
but to say that you know what what's
happening in
um say
um motor control where top-down signals
from the cortex go down to the ganglia
in the in the spinal cord in order to
invoke motor patterns
um
to call that a prediction is to me a
kind of um well that's that's taking
Extreme Measures to map the concepts of
the theory onto
what neurons are doing
and um you know if the theory works out
to be
you know very useful in some way and
that's what you have to do to to make
that happen
okay I guess I can use that language but
it operatory it just does not seem like
the right language to use to say yeah
we're trying to to set up some motor
patterns set up some some context and
situations for what we want the you know
the local reflexes and and to be doing
um but to cast that as a prediction just
seems a little unnatural to me
so those are my two reactions to this
chapter
thank you
anyone else with a raised hand
this is a really
good point about what
the linkage or mapping is between
uh without going into like you know is
anything physical or Etc like
physical brains in their Niche and any
type of equations
would a well-fitting linear model say
that the brain is a linear model
does a well-fitting base graph imply
that the brain is a base graph
does a well-fitting base graph plus a
philosophical belief that we're just
making a map we're not describing the
territory equate to what
Beyond a linear model or a verbal model
Rohan
yeah building on the previous point
right uh
I am still unsure what what uh active
inference is considering a signal
there's no effective
well there's no noise model or there's
it it doesn't specify that here's
because if you if you say
uh that I'm predicting something right
so there must be something that is
substantially different statistically
different from some noise distribution
that you can differentiate right so
it's basically trying to estimate some
hidden probabilities which is not really
Sigma
does it make sense because yours even
the internal States unless they're
actually
uh instantiated prior like when we set
up the model we say okay these are the
only states that you can actually
Traverse
it does not make you still have to infer
the States from your measurements of
reality
thank you
foreign
yeah I just
um
wanted to ask if the noise isn't kind of
implied in
um the pomdp formalism
like uh I think in figure 5.4
um
where it shows the direct and invert
Pathways with message passing
um
it describes
active in the basic ganglia
as a umdp generative model so if it's
partially observable doesn't that imply
some kind of noise
uh my counter to this would be uh that
is missing information that needs to be
filled out that's not really noise rate
uh so noise would be something
like if we
uh like it so even if we let's let's not
use this right it would be some so we
have like returns of a stock
and looking at the distribution of of
the prior returns we know what the
spread is and in case we we want to
measure whether your portfolio is
substantially different from this
distribution that's where we would have
some sort of like sharp Ratio or a
signal to noise ratio noise ratio being
the complete set of distributions that
are possible
this set of ranges that are possible
uh that is not really here because it
that is missing information so we can
only observe part the fact that we have
only partial observations does not
excuse the fact that we don't have
uh even noise models of the sensors so
how good are the sensors for example
I do we have some idea of that
yes but then I'll add a point about
these Bayesian terminology
yeah um
yes
um is there is there any like what's the
Practical difference between partial
observation where there's where the
noise
implies some kind of
information that is missing versus like
a distribution that's added to full
observation that
um
adds noise to like the sensory
processing
great so it so that would be some okay
so if I use an actual physical sensor
right
uh it would be something like what are
the ranges of values that it can go up
to because we've designed the sensor
so we would we basically know what the
bias is what the variance of the sensor
is under different conditions
uh there are actual physical processes
implied in that measurement so in the
case of uh
ultrasonic sensors probably like some
current value or some voltage value
that's being measured by some circuitry
somewhere so there are ranges for that
so it there's no missing information
there
so you basically know
so it's already prior in this system
right so you know what the ranges of
values are going to be and from there
you need to infer the some state in the
world so is there an obstacle in the way
or is there yeah
okay let me just make a comment about
some basic terminology then um Jessica
and Brock so let's look at figure
4.3 this is the partially observable
uh Markov decision process that Jacob
talked about but we're going to be just
talking about the perceptive part not
the action intervention into how things
are changing get just focusing on this
Motif on the left like step-by-step
guide uses
so
um you mentioned about the the bias
related to measurements so if
the measurables are the observable sense
States then the bias and the covariance
and the variance
about how like the reading on the
thermometer relates to the underlying
variable the the hidden State the
temperature of the room it's embodied in
the a matrix
because that is actually the learned or
fixed variable
that is
playing a role of a noise model
then you mentioned when talking about
Returns on stocks testing whether
there's like a substantial difference
from some null expectation like is there
a signal that's different from the noise
um this is like a frequentist approach
it's based upon determining whether
there's some statistically significant
level doesn't have to be it's not the
only way to do it
um but one can do like a p-value on
whether a given signal is statistically
different from given a noise model
different from noise and then like the
sharp ratio and other types of things
are like summary statistics they're like
descriptive statistics
um
noisy measurements
are addressed in the context of the
pomdp
by having
an a matrix that accommodates some of
the features of denoising a signal
and then Precision variables
and those precisions can again be
learned or fixed
but like the functional
um
aspects of what is being referred to as
noisy measurements
are accommodated within this kind of
Bayesian approach which is why common
filtering generalized Bayesian filtering
why these techniques are used because we
can have a Bayesian update scheme
implemented with with variational
approaches message passing sampling all
these things
that does denoise signal and it does
embody a noise model and a signal model
and that's all part of the generative
model of the cognitive entity
so it just isn't being addressed from a
frequent to statistics or
um
yeah I shouldn't have brought up the
sharp ratio maybe that's not the best
but the sharp ratio is uh
is effectively some way to say that some
portfolio choice is different from
others or in communication systems you
would see use something like EB over n0
that's the signal noise ratio for any
sort of communication system
so yeah yeah uh but they're not
necessarily only frequentest right so we
there are patient ways to estimate these
things in fact that's pretty much how we
do it in practice because we we don't
assume
uh that we know the uh complete
distribution we update priors in each of
these cases because we have
yeah
uh
coming back to your point that the a
matrix does address this the a matrix
would be something that would you said
it would denoise and filter out some
stray observations but okay so our so
the the question Still Remains is when
you're saying prediction is a prediction
of the signal over here
as in what is the future state of the
sensor
but I think there it seems seemed to
indicate that the prediction relates to
relates to the free energy minimization
itself right so you choose policies that
would minimize your free energy and keep
yourself into some set point
so which means that there should be some
sort of uh
an idea of what ranges are there for
this value or uh how far can these go
before
you know you're not in that set point
anymore
so even if you if you do want to make
that prediction it's a it's not just the
signal value so signal values
effectively through the Marco blanket
they affect some internal State and
we're that's what I I'm assuming that's
what we're trying to predict the
trajectory of the future internal States
actually the expectation that's being
um yeah minimized is over outcome
observations not about internal States
oh okay yeah yeah I'm sorry so uh yeah
so even then we we don't have so the
signals may have well-defined precision
and bias but
the entire system itself doesn't have
any sort of
uh
well it doesn't know how wrong it could
go
it doesn't have any error estimate so
that it's it there's no noise model as
such so we can't apply any so we would
have to assume that there is some
distribution of states and then use
something like least squares or some
other uh optimization routine to
actually bring this in practice
great totally possible um it would be
interesting to sketch out a Bayes graph
for what you believe a signal to noise
or some type of noise model would embody
and maybe we will see some analogies or
some mappings
um Jessica and then Brock
hi yes I'm I mean I think
I both you and Rohan like in the new
Province but
I was going to say that um
would be like the filtering and like a
lot of like the biases and things like
that kind of like made sense of it is
like
I see the because I think it was like
chapter two or something like that I
said like right like so the why is
this you know quote-unquote
um you know uh like a fat thing like you
know that we can observe from the hidden
state or like the process of something
that we don't know and so for everybody
like we can see the same thing but how
we process it internally is going to
vary like it's gonna be very subjective
so the why is gonna look different for
Daniel then it's gonna look for me based
on all this filtering and so the black
Estates
I imagine sort of like one half like
those filters that encode the biases and
all the things that allow us to
process things differently and and so
like then I generated model
and it would like it's gonna be updated
like differently all right also like
encoded I think in the general model
would be a lot of uh like you reset and
things like that that embody I think
probably like a lot of biases and like
things of how we understand things which
also influence how we
interpret what we observe
and so for so for me it's like a lot of
these things are there like in terms of
like statistics I don't know um much but
that's how like I you know conceptually
I um
but like you know understood like a lot
of these things so like basically like
in the blanket stage of the Marco
blanket
it would have a ladder like this
filtering you know and
yes like
um like if you're going to try to you
know let's say Like You observe
something that's different than what you
predicted in your model then you would
take action and to forage and like find
information
and to figure it out okay like what am I
missing like why did I make this mistake
or like this error I in my prediction
and so that I can like have more
information and update the model so that
it aligns more closely so then you would
basically take action to the noise and
basically get closer to
um like quote unquote the reality that's
out there
that yeah I don't know if it's official
lighting but that's how like it kind of
makes sense to me
thanks Jessica Brock
um yeah I just
uh
wanted to I guess speak to this like
uh sensor noise model I don't like in
practice in reality like when you're
talking about sensors like in a physical
system like like a digital signal
processing kind of context like
the sensors are tested under some
conditions for things like you know
Jitter and
um spurious kind of uh noise conditions
and stuff like that but they're tested
under some conditions
meaning that there's never ever going to
be a time when you have an actual model
you're just going to have an
approximation whether that's expressed
in a frequentis or Bayesian
um
way like there's going to be some
uncertainty in the model
and especially if you start connecting
it up to
a larger system
um doing the same kind of like is the
Jitter in that sensor the same when you
know when it's completely isolated as it
is when it's on a you know six by nine
PCB board with you know
um
12 volts on one side and a oscillator
next to that that's you know like
are those now is it the same thing you
know
um you have to do these sort of
electromagnetic compatibility you know
resonance sort of testing on it like
there's just that it's it's uh in
practice it's Bayesian like you're doing
the same sort of
um bounding and you know belief
um testing and you know Finding Your
errors and correcting them
um even in practice
[Music]
um
I don't see how you could possibly have
like even like physically a system like
that could exist where you had a noise
model that you could write down that was
actually the noise model
um under all conditions or
yeah it's um
it doesn't seem like a
approachable I don't know it's not even
not tractable
which is the wrong thing to do I don't
thanks Brock
um in the case of engineering and
designing models it's up to the designer
or the engineering team to understand
like what is adequate or not and for
natural systems
outside of their bounds
natural selection sweeps them off the
table
so some of the adequacy questions are
either based upon
specified or implicit human standards or
the failure to resist
dissipation
and therefore the failure to realize
repeated measurements
of oneself or from the external
and then that system is no longer
let's just continue to move through some
of the questions
um yes go for it
uh yeah I I completely agree with what
Brock said right but my my point was
when when you say that you're predicting
something it means that
uh you either know the quantity that
you're trying to predict
and or and it corresponds to so in this
case like some action results in some
reward I guess you could predict the
reward but without knowing how wrong
you're going to be in the future
so
where exactly immigrant is so that any
living system would have to have be
aware of its own bounds right that's
that's what I meant by noise models so
it has to know that it has to stay
within some bounds and as it starts
coming closer to one of the upper lower
bounds there should be some something
like pulling it back down
or some feedback mechanism but that is
not very clear from the from what I've
read so far on active inference system
what
how exactly it would estimate that is
you can just save free energy
minimization
uh but what is a minimum in this case
that would be different for different
systems so it should have some idea of
where the surfaces of whichever local
surface it's lying on that that was my
point
so for sure it's different for different
systems it's different as every single
generative model is
um and then you mentioned like
um a pullback attractor and so this has
been treated extensively in the context
of physiological measurements and then
again wear those priors on the
physiological measurements are the
tolerable range are either provided by
the human engineering team or through
evolution by natural selection and then
um yeah
the quantity like another related topic
would be expectation maximization models
which is what is happening essentially
in the dialectic between the observation
and the hidden State update
is an expectation maximization like
process where it's like given the hyper
priors
or we can just simplify just given the
priors on S what are the most likely or
the distribution of observables and then
given the observables what should be
updated about the hidden State priors
and when those are at conversions the
model is stationary and then as things
change either from the top via learning
or context shift or through changed
measurements
the expectation maximization algorithm
is just able to track those changes and
that can in the context of a fixed prior
have the function of a pullback
attractor
um okay and that's even before getting
into action specifically but yes
definitely considering like the role of
comparing future plans of action
and which plans of actions will have the
least expected free energy based upon
their
um pragmatic and epistemic value like
which the epistemic just being Clarity
around how it's going to be achieved and
the pragmatic value being that KL
Divergence between the expectations
preferences and the expected
observations
so if we expect slash prefer to be in
homeostasis
the pragmatic value is going to come or
be loaded onto policies that keep us in
homeostasis even if some other one is
super informative
how that model gets tuned is quite
literally the details of how the model
is
trained right my point was that active
inference doesn't help us find this we
have to find this ourselves and then
hopefully once we have instantiated
these bounds I think active inference
works very well to keep it within this
right if you can't discover this you
know right like I can't have like a uh
what you'd say double or rasa type
system like a blank slave system God in
the world and discover your bounds
that's not going to happen but this kind
of method is what what I was uh making
it out whereas
taking some something equivalent without
any so deep learning is another
uh method right so you just feed it a
lot of data it doesn't have to know
anything about the data eventually it
forms some opinion about the data it's
seen and then it's able to do some
classification or depending on how much
data it's seen so it's able to build
certain amount of bounds whether that's
generalizable is a different question
but
uh here there's the learning part
does not say much about how exactly it
goes about discovering
where its limits are that that's my
point
sure thank you
um Eric
um you know I would I would love to to
dive this a little bit more into
um the thing you were just talking about
how expectation maximization might is a
is a mathematical
formulation for how to infer belief
States from observations because you uh
basically go through this iterative
process of trying to find alignment
between the states of the belief and the
observables and then you can track that
over time
between that concept and the concept of
message passing
when I think of message passing I think
of some sort of a distributed system
where you have some local computation
and it sends you know and you have again
either synchronous or Acres asynchronous
process for
communicating between these kind of
different centers of
cut of belief state
and then again through message passing
you have often an iterative process of
convergence
so um those are not the same thing and I
think you know message passing to my
understanding would be an em algorithm
under certain types of messages and
States at each of the nodes that you're
sending the messages around but not all
message passing is going to be any em
algorithm and similarly when I think of
em I don't think about message passing I
think about making an arrays of you know
of um
belief and matrices between you know
mapping between belief and observations
and then
um trying to compute an expectation for
you know for for what my predictions
would be and then making this iterative
conversion so I don't think of that in
terms of message passing so I'd like to
I just love to hear other people's ideas
about how to tie these two
um ideas together
yeah
um Brock
if your hand is still raced or
okay nope so sorry yeah okay all good
um
does anyone have thoughts on this
there's a lot to say about the uh
expectation maximization algorithms and
like just to kind of give a little
context this is the step-by-step
um paper
so this is the model stream one it's
four parts
um and this is like really a quite
relevant figure which is not in the
textbook
but helps a lot like this is the essence
of the partially observable Bayesian
inference there's a prior D and then
there's an a ambiguity Matrix that is
mapping in a generative capacity between
hidden States s and observation
measurements o this is The Tail of Two
densities because o
through a can give you the most likely s
an S through a can give you the most
likely o
and it turns out that by alternating
those procedures
in a Bayesian update context
that two-stroke engine is called
expectation maximization again because
given expectations on the summary
statistics of a distribution the
expected sensory observations can be
generated and then given those
observations a likelihood function can
be maximized that then updates the
hidden States so this Motif this kind of
elbow motif
is then extended into a caterpillar with
this B
which is how the hidden State changes
their time
so importantly like note what's not
there which is like the observations
being chained Through Time
so it's not that the temperature reading
at one moment influences the temperature
reading at the next moment the
temperature readings are continually
linked
um synchronously like in one time slice
to their hidden States
so then when action gets into the
picture
we've talked about like several sources
that's like the equation 2.5 to equation
2.6 phase change because action brings
in several kinds of uncertainty first
off you're reducing your uncertainty
about observations which haven't
happened yet
you're also having the unknown
consequences of your actions
and in order to have action selection
that's relevance one has to have a
preference distribution
over what kinds of observations they
would like to be seeing so that action
can guide it in that direction
okay
um then so that's the the expectation
maximization two-stroke engine
is basically graphically
um proposed here D is just the
initiating set of parameters
and then in a One-Shot way like you can
have a a folder with a thousand images
and do expectation maximization on it
or you could have something that's
dynamical and do that type of
expectation maximization Through Time
[Music]
um
Eric asked how is it related to
message passing
on graphs so I'm not familiar with all
the details of this model but you
basically said it which was that like
certain message passing systems
Implement em
but of course not all message patching
architectures Implement DM so message
passing is more General than em also em
wouldn't have to be implemented through
message passing so there's kind of but
there's like an area of intersection
where the EM algorithm can be seen as a
type of message passing
under certain compute rules in a factor
graph
and EM at least from here may be used to
break Cycles in a factor graph
so it's always like
how close to the kernel and like the
platonic ideal of active inference are
we talking
and then how many heuristics
and just
ways of connecting things are possible
so I
I will now read the chat
that's from previous context okay okay
thank you
um
like the statistical parametric mapping
textbook and documentation SPM
has a lot on em
variational inference
and a lot of the parts that bring one
to understand this
a lot better SPM is like almost like it
doesn't include action that much because
it's a neuroimaging so the observations
are neuroimaging Sensor Fusion different
error modalities like the whole panopoly
and then SPM started to incorporate
participant actions
in this partially observable metabasian
way and potentially that is what led
Tristan colleagues towards a grander
synthesis of inference and action
under a statistically principled
framework
let's just see if there's any other
these are all you know
important questions and like there's a
lot to get up to them and then there's
like a lot to go from the question but
these are all important things to raise
okay
[Music]
um
if anyone has a thought on this how
should we think about redundancy in
neural systems in the context of active
inference
so redundancy would be like if there's
something that's playing a functional
role but it's removal
is not damaging the function of the
system yeah there's 10 pillars knocking
out one of them the building stays up
so there's redundancy in the pillars
what about the cases where the same
neural circuits serves multiple
functions
so how do we deal with the fact that
there's like a many-to-many potentially
or a complex mapping between system
elements and system functions
where sometimes removing Node 1 does
nothing but removing node one and two
there's a lot of things but then
removing one two and three and it's
going back to being fine Jessica
and maybe like ask blue about it because
this is what I feel but
it this question made me think about
like it's not only like that the brain
has like this redundancy things but
it like would like to say like if you
have some kind of damage to your brain
like another part of your brain that
maybe you was not
use for something would develop that
capacity
and so it would create that you know
ability
and so neuroplasticity like
brand new even though it was not a
redundancy to begin with so I guess I'm
more Curious to understand this and so
other people who know more like blue and
stuff um
about this and basically that's kind of
what this question made me think about
and kind of wanting to understand more
that's good question yeah blue wrote
depends on your age yeah like difference
neuroplasticity mechanisms are
differentially available throughout life
for different organisms
um
Just one thought on this would be like
the same neural circuit serving multiple
functions might be totally the case for
example
um and one like is the function of a
heart to provide one pound of weight to
the Torso it is a function of the heart
is at one you know so identifying what
function is being modeled is what's
being done here so let's just go to like
the example of figure five three
this
neuron
modifying it like a loss of function
experiments or having it injured might
influence more things than just
the lower motor neuron descending
message
so that'd be a case where like it serves
multiple functions
um
this is just one statistical model
of
this function of this circuit
and that returns to to the earliest
comments of Eric with like okay this is
like tantalizingly seeming like it's
actually going to be describing the
neural Anatomy but then they say things
like note the absence of dot dot dot dot
note that there's a discrepancy between
for example
the reality of the anatomy
and the base graph
this highlights that the connections
implied by message passing schemes may
not manifest as single synapses
so
okay
there's kind of false positives and
false negatives the Bayes graph isn't
just the anatomy
that's fine
the linear regression between height and
weight isn't the actual relationship
between height and weight and the
structural equation model of
inequality is not the generator of
inequality
so it's totally fair and shouldn't be
expected to be otherwise that the base
graph the best fitting base graph the
most didactic phase graph the simplest
phase graph
none of those recapitulate the anatomy
and the base graph that recapitulates
the anatomy would not necessarily even
be the best fitting
its map and territory
and if somebody has a a special equation
to break through that
blanket
everybody would love to see it
however
sometimes it's easy to gloss over
that
in principle challenge
of mapping formalisms to biological
systems because we see the cell and then
the blanket is the membrane and we see
the brain and it's like vision and
action and it seems like it maps on to
the physical or the anatomical structure
of the world or the causal structure of
the world
and um
it doesn't
so I hope people can add more thoughts
about like how we consider redundancy
because it's a great
question
um
but we'll leave it there
um how are
reflexes modeled in active inference
would they exist in an active inference
module that is distinct from
proprioception but they operate on
different time scales
um if anybody wants to add like some
some context on it
um
a reflex arc
relating to
um where reflex is defined as
um a function that is being relayed
through the spinal cord of a mammal
and not passing like you could have a
nerve block in the cervical vertebra and
it still is able to like Implement like
that's one definition of reflex
often it's also used slightly more
broadly to mean like
um stimulus action reproducible outcomes
but not every reflex has a perfect
reproducibility et cetera et cetera so
it's kind of a Continuum
um yes it would involve proprioceptive
input
that proprioceptive input
would be combined or
um
juxtaposed with the descending
prediction
resulting in an error
and then that directionality and
magnitude of the error in this model
drives the reflex
there can also be multiple time scales
but we haven't seen any nested modeling
yet
this is just the one layer model
the schematic on the left in figure five
one
shows that layer 5 of Cortex projects to
spinal pyramidal neurons and this can be
interpreted as a prediction
okay so this is this one
um
okay helpful um context
and and it um relates to this earlier
highlighted section
which is like
it's the interpretation
the interpretive link
between some anatomical or biological
feature phenotype
and some parametric
resonance with a model
the validity of that ranges from
pretty clear
pretty uncontroversial pretty useful
pretty effective
to
none of the above
and it's hard to know like what given
interpretive links
are doing
like saying that this Edge on this base
graph can be interpreted as a descending
excitatory connection
or that might be used to generate
specific testable hypotheses like if we
measure it during a period of excitation
the activity of this neuron we expect it
to be increased whereas if it was a
descending inhibitory connection
Etc
um
that's a great example of active
inference being used in a proactive way
to generate hypotheses about biological
systems that are going to be as they
said in the preface
[Music]
um
answerable to measured data
by grounding in
the computational model
that is related to the neural Anatomy
but isn't trying to be like a digital
twin of the neuroanatomy
we can generate predictions about gain
loss of function different measurements
to make if they don't already exist
and then that can be used to increase
our confidence or reliability or falsify
even a specific generative model as
proposed
so there's so much discourse like
continuing to the present day and surely
Beyond as like all these questions and
recently posted in the Discord about
like
active inference or free energy
principle isn't falsifiable
now the funny link is it's not
falsifiable so it's been falsified
it can't be falsified
so it's incorrect
that's an interesting connection that
some people make but a linear model
cannot be falsified a base graph cannot
be falsified once any given linear model
is presented
in a context with constraints for a
certain data type
then it's an empirical question of its
accuracy and adequacy relative to other
models
but at the abstract level of a neural
network or linear model or active
inference
falsification
simply doesn't apply
but there's a lot that could be
clarified
um
about like what are the utilities and
some of the pitfalls
of mapping
biological or cyber physical systems to
active inference models
if it's a purely digital system or
potentially even a cyber physical system
that's been designed a really certain
way
it might be compatible with actinth
like essentially by Fiat or by Design
one could make an artificial creature
like an infra ant
that is implementing active inference
one could also model an ant in the field
using a linear model or a levy flight or
some other model or an active inference
model
but those are two very different
settings one in which sort of the rabbit
was placed into the Hat
and then we have a rabbit analyzer
and the other one being like
we don't know what's in the Hat but we
have a rapid analyzer that we think
applies to what is in this hat
um
chapter five includes some
um evidence presented on different
neurotransmitters so
um it'd be interesting to see like
what other Frameworks
are able to be compatible
or even provide unique explanations
predictions Etc
related to neurochemistry
have neural networks ever been used to
derive unique predictions or found
compatibility with neural hormones
neurochemicals
um
and then again they have a final figure
in chapter five that's like a graphical
overview of several of the systems that
are described in the chapter
specifically relating to like the
cortical
cognitive functions
and then
the dialectic between habit and
free energy driven planning
here
with dopamine as a Precision modulator
with like extensive further modeling
presented in other papers and this like
even more basal
motor selection mechanism based upon
reflex arcs and proprioceptive error
minimization
and all of that
um
we raise these questions not to offer
any answers but to highlight some of the
exciting Avenues of future research and
theoretical neurobiology
so a lot of the questions that are asked
um
here in this paragraph but also above at
the very beginning they said we're not
saying how it is we're just giving like
the current process model understanding
and then especially at the end
they raise even more speculative
questions
so
um that takes us to the end of chapter
five
that's the first half of the book that's
the uh epistemic component of the book
well a lot of it is epistemic but that's
the first five chapters
um
the second five chapters
which are longer
partially because of having more figures
and things like that but you can see
there's more pages
um slightly in the second
part of the book though we've also read
the um
at least some of the appendices
that's where we're heading which is
picking up on uh
chapter six in just a few weeks with a
recipe for Designing active Emperors
models so for those who stuck with the
uncertainty
for the first five chapters and stay in
the game
more will become clear when the recipe
for the dish is seen and then more will
be
clarified when the dish is prepared and
then when
you cut the vegetables and then when you
design the dish in the recipe and all of
that and that's like a journey that
we're all going to be on the tools are
not finalized in the kitchen is not
completed Etc et cetera et cetera so
it's just a call for us to go to
onboarding
and indicate our interest in continuing
with one or the other uh cohort
or sharing with any colleagues who you
think might like to jump in to the
second cohort of part one
and then in the coming two weeks
we'll be able to take a step back
look over the chapter questions but also
think about more general questions that
we're having basic questions
miso questions Advanced questions
research Avenues and also turn to the
project ideas
where multiple of these are already
active and there's spaces for people who
want to
facilitate or catalyze some other
direction
so
fun meeting
everyone's welcome to uh stay on for
tools or head up to a room above if they
just want to talk to other people about
anything else
so thanks again for joining and see you
in just a few minutes for tools